Guide to the Joseph Katz Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Joseph Katz papers
1951-1988
SC0979
Katz, Joseph, 1920-
8.5 Linear feet
Collection includes the following: Vassar College student interviews and report to the college president, 1951; interviews and other materials for the Student Development Studies done at the Institute for the Study of Human Problems, 1960-85; interviews with Stanford students from an unknown study, 1961-77; interviews, correspondence, and final report from the Ford Foundation Project on Teaching and Learning, 1984-88; questionnaires, audio interviews, correspondence, and other papers from the Guggenheim Project on German University Students, 1978-79; articles, memos, clippings, reports, etc., pertaining to Katz’s work at the Institute for the Study of Human Problems, 1962-80; professional correspondence, 1964-88; Katz’s reprints, articles, books, and unpublished works; and biographical information on Katz.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Joseph Katz came to Stanford University in 1961 as Research Coordinator at the Institute for the Study of Human Problems; he was executive director when he left in 1970 to join the faculty at SUNY Stony Brook. Educated at the University of Pennsylvania, M.A. 1942, and Columbia, Ph.D. 1948, Katz taught philosophy at Vassar College, 1948-1961, and was a research associate in psychiatry at UC Berkeley, 1958-60. While at Stanford he conducted a five-year longitudinal study of students (drawn from Stanford and UC Berkeley), which became the basis for the book NO TIME FOR YOUTH.
Description of the Collection
Collection includes the following: Vassar College student interviews and report to the college president, 1951; interviews and other materials for the Student Development Studies done at the Institute for the Study of Human Problems, 1960-85; interviews with Stanford students from an unknown study, 1961-77; interviews, correspondence, and final report from the Ford Foundation Project on Teaching and Learning, 1984-88; questionnaires, audio interviews, correspondence, and other papers from the Guggenheim Project on German University Students, 1978-79; articles, memos, clippings, reports, etc., pertaining to Katz’s work at the Institute for the Study of Human Problems, 1962-80; professional correspondence, 1964-88; Katz’s reprints, articles, books, and unpublished works; and biographical information on Katz.
Access Terms
Katz, Joseph, 1920-; Stanford University. Institute for the Study of Human Problems.; Vassar College--Students.; College students--Germany.; College students--United States.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH 2010-014
  - C.V with photo; biographical articles (Box 1)
  - Katz’s reprints and articles (Box 1)
  - Unpublished articles, reports, proposals, teaching plans and notes (Box 1)
  - Unpublished scholarly articles (Box 1)
  - Published works: Growth and Constraint in College Students, 1967; The Student Affairs Dean and the President: Trends in Higher Education, 1979; Writers on Ethics, 1973; and No Time for Youth, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Student Development Studies (Institute for the Study of Human Problems). Interviews, 1960-75 (Box 2)
  - Interviews with Stanford students (unknown study – not Stud. Devel. Studies), 1961-77 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation Project Interviews, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Final Report on the Ford Foundation Project on Teaching and Learning by Mildred M. Henry and Joseph Katz, April 1988 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and interim papers, Ford Foundation Project on Teaching and Learning, 1984-87 (Box 3)
  - Institute for the Study of Human Problems [ISHP]: articles, memos, clippings, reports, etc., 1962-80 (Box 3)
  - ISHP Berkeley faculty interviews, 1959 (Box 3)
  - ISHP miscellaneous questionnaires and interview transcripts (Box 3)
  - Vassar College student interviews and report to the college president, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Joseph Katz professional correspondence, 1964-88 (Box 3)
  - Working papers, Group for Human Development and Educational Policy, SUNY Stony Brook, 1973-82 (Box 3)
  - Two chapters from Anthology on Adult Women (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and interviews, University Presidents Study, 1977-82 (Box 3)
  - Published works: Turning Professors into Teachers, 1988; Teaching Undergraduates, Essays from the Lilly Endowment workshop on Liberal Arts, 1988; Search for Relevance, 1969; and Scholars in the Making, 1976 (Box 3)
  - Guggenheim Project on German University Students, correspondence, reports and interviews, 1979-80 (Box 4)
  - Guggenheim Project on German University Students, interviews and research, 1978-79 (Box 4)
  - Guggenheim Project on German University Students, assorted materials (Box 4)
  - ISHP, follow-up interviews for student development study, 1961-85 (Box 4)
  - German project questionnaires (Box 4)
  - Guggenheim Project, correspondence, interviews and relevant research, 1978-79 (Box 4)
  - Guggenheim Project, report, 1979 (Box 4)
  - German project: unsorted miscellany, mostly clippings and articles (Box 5)
  - interviews for Guggenheim Project on German University students, 4 audiocassette(s) (Box 5)
  - Joseph Katz & Carol Gillighan “Developing a Theory of Human Development”; Joseph Katz research re teachers; and Shari Cohn interviewing Dr. Joseph Katz at Stony Brook, Jan. 6, 1987; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 5)
  - Audio cassettes: interviews for Guggenheim Project on German University students, 1978-79 (Box 6)
  - Audio cassettes: interviews for Guggenheim Project on German University students, 1978-79 (Box 7)